# Areej AlBahar

### Ph.D. Student in Industrial and Systems Engineering at Virginia Tech

Blacksburg, VA, U.S.A.

■ areejaa3@vt.edu | ► Areej AlBahar

### **Research Statement**

I am a Ph.D. student in the Grado Department of Industrial and Systems Engineering at Virginia Tech. I work in the Machine Learning for Advanced Manufacturing Laboratory headed by Dr. Xiaowei Yue. My research interests include statistical quality control and machine learning, nonparametric regression and Gaussian processes, Bayesian modeling, and sequential design.

### Education

## Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University (Virginia Tech)

Ph.D. in Industrial and Systems Engineering

**University of Florida** 

M.S. IN INDUSTRIAL AND SYSTEMS ENGINEERING

Kuwait University

B.S. IN INDUSTRIAL AND MANAGEMENT SYSTEMS ENGINEERING

Blacksburg, VA, USA

Aug. 2016 - present

Gainesville, FL, USA

Jan. 2015 - May. 2016

Khaldiya, Kuwait

Sep. 2008 - Jan. 2013

## **Publications**

### **JOURNAL ARTICLES**

A Robust Asymmetric Kernel Function for Bayesian Optimization, With Application to Image Defect Detection in Manufacturing Systems

Areej AlBahar, Inyoung Kim, Xiaowei Yue

IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering (2021) pp. 1–12. 2021

### Physics-Constrained Bayesian Optimization

Areej AlBahar, Inyoung Kim, Xing Wang, Xiaowei Yue

IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering (under revision) (2021). 2021

### Nested Bayesian Optimization for Computer Experiments

Yan Wang, Meng Wang, Areej AlBahar, Xiaowei Yue

IEEE Transactions on Mechatronics (under revision) (2021). 2021

## Stress-Aware Optimal Placement of Actuators for High Precision Quality Control of Composite Structures Assembly

Areej AlBahar, Inyoung Kim, Tim Lutz, Xiaowei Yue

IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters (under review) (2022). 2022

### Honors & Awards \_\_

## NAMRC 49 / MSEC 2021 NSF Student Support Award

VIRGINIA TECH

22<sup>nd</sup> Annual Outstanding International Student Award

UNIVERSITY OF FLORIDA

21st Annual Outstanding International Student Award

University of Florida

Full scholarship to pursue M.S. and Ph.D. degrees in the USA

KUWAIT UNIVERSITY SCHOLARSHIP PROGRAM

Blacksurg, VA, USA

April 2021

Gainesville, FL, USA
Nov. 2016

1101. 2010

Gainesville, FL, USA

Nov. 2015

Khaldiya, Kuwait

Dec. 2014

### **Dean's Honor list and Outstanding Students list**

COLLEGE OF ENGINEERING AND PETROLEUM, KUWAIT UNIVERSITY

**Second Place Winner** 

KUWAIT REGIONAL MATHEMATICAL OLYMPIAD

Khaldiya, Kuwait

2009 - 2013

Kuwait 2007

## Work Experience\_

### **Graduate Research Assistant**

VIRGINIA TECH

Blacksburg, VA, USA

Feb. 2022 - present

#### **Graduate Research Assistant**

VIRGINIA TECH

Blacksburg, VA, USA

Oct. 2021 - Nov. 2021

### **Facility Management Engineer**

KUWAIT UNIVERSITY

Khaldiya, Kuwait Dec. 2013 - Dec. 2014

Certifications: ISO 9001:2008 Foundation Training, Fundamentals of Occupational Health and Safety Systems, Problem Solving For Managers, and ISO 9001 for Quality Management Systems.

## Research Experience \_

## Sep. 2021 - present

### Stress-Aware Optimal Placement of Actuators in Composite Fuselages

In this work, we incorporate physical constraints (e.g., stress) into the Bayesian optimization framework. We propose a safe sequential sampling strategy to minimize exploration of hazardous regions while optimizing the response surface function in a minimum number of function evaluations.

### Jan. 2021 - Sep. 2021

### **Physics-Constrained Bayesian Optimization**

In this work, we address the challenges of optimizing constrained non-stationary and expensive-to-evaluate engineering response surface functions with constrained Bayesian optimization. Most existing non-stationary approaches are still ineffective in accurately modeling complex nonstationary functions. We propose a multi-layer deep Gaussian process mean function which improves the applicability of constrained Bayesian optimization to complex non-linear and non-stationary processes.

### Jan. 2020 - Dec. 2020

## Image Defect Detection in Manufacturing Systems

In this work, we address the challenges of approximating complex, nonlinear, and expensive-to-evaluate engineering response surface functions with Bayesian optimization. Most existing kernel functions are vulnerable and susceptible to outliers; the existence of outliers causes the Gaussian process model to be sporadic. We propose an asymmetric kernel function to create a Bayesian optimization model that is robust to outliers. We use the proposed framework in hyperparameter tuning of deep learning models.

### Jan. 2018 - Oct. 2019

### **Predictive Modelling for Online Quality Process Monitoring**

I focus heavily on deep learning models; more specifically, predictive neural networks and their performance. By employing quality control and data analytics concepts, I model series of images as inputs to recurrent and convolutional neural networks in order to predict future instances, I then use the predicted instances for quality classification. Bayesian optimization and unsupervised learning schemes are the methods I am currently exploring to improve those neural networks performances.

## **Teaching Experience**

### **Teaching Assistant - Operations Research II**

DEPARTMENT OF INDUSTRIAL AND MANAGEMENT SYSTEMS ENGINEERING, KUWAIT UNIVERSITY

Fall 2013

• Office hours and grading

### **Teaching Assistant - Reliability and Maintainability Engineering**

DEPARTMENT OF INDUSTRIAL AND MANAGEMENT SYSTEMS ENGINEERING, KUWAIT UNIVERSITY

• Office hours and grading

Khaldiya, Kuwait

Khaldiya, Kuwait

Fall 2013

## Professional Service \_\_\_\_\_

Reviewer

Journal of Intelligent Manufacturing ('20)

## References \_\_\_\_\_

### Xiaowei Yue (Academic primary co-advisor)

Assistant Professor Department of Industrial and Systems Engineering Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA

xwy@vt.edu

(+1) 540-231-9081

### Inyoung Kim (Academic co-advisor)

Associate Professor Department of Statistics Virginia Tech Blacksburg, VA

inyoungk@vt.edu (+1) 540-231-5366